So we have the assignment where we can create a person and we populate name and age randomly or the
Dolaysyla, bir kii yaratabildiimiz atamamz var ve adn ve yan rasgele ya da
age randomly,
rasgele dolduruyoruz.
the name is hard coded in the reducer.
Bu isim yapmcda zor kodlanyor.
Of course it would be a typical use case to have input fields for the user to use to specify these values,
Elbette, kullanclarn bu deerleri belirtmek iin kullanaca giri alanlar iin tipik bir kullanm durumu olurdu.
how would that work?
Bu nasl ie yarar?
It's a typical case of local UI state, you did of course learn over the last modules in this course
Yerel gzlemlerin tipik bir rneidir, tabii ki bu ekirdein son modlleri zerinde renmi
that for user input, we also handle this with set state and in the state in general and for that,
olduunuz durum, kullanc girii iin hepimizin bahsedilen devletle ve genel olarak devlette olduu ve bunun iin
we don't need to use redux just to store the value the user input, we need it
redoks kullanmamz gerekmesidir sadece deerini kullanc girdisi olarak saklamak iin.
then if we want to create a person with that input but just to handle each keystroke and use two-way
Dan, bu girdiyi ieren bir kii yaratmak istiyorsak, ancak her tu vuruunu halletmek ve
binding, we don't necessarily use redux.
balayc kullanmakta iseniz, mutlaka yeniden ynlendirme kullanmamza gerek yoktur.
So in addPerson where we have our button, let's say we now also add inputs and I'll make this very simple,
Dolaysyla u anda bizim dmemize nerede girdiimizi de syleyelim, imdi de giriler eklemeliyiz ve bunu,
I'll add an input of type text with a placeholder of name and then a second one with age,
bir yer tutucusu olan ad metni girii olarak ve daha sonra H ile ikinci bir metin olarak basitletireceiz.
and this will be of type number,
Ve bunlar tip numaras olacak.
so super simple input fields here which allow us to add a person.
Bu nedenle, bir kii eklememize izin veren sper basit giri alanlar.
Now we can turn AddPerson into a component using the class keyword to manage the state of these inputs,
imdi, bu girdileri tkamak iin ynetmek iin class anahtar kelimesini kullanarak bir kiiyi bir bileene dntrebiliriz.
let's simply do that, I'll add components here into the import and turn this into a class, class addPerson with
snfn bedeninde Trans-Am GSX olduumuzun render yntemine sahip olacaz; daha nce kullandmz GSX'dir.
a capital character extends the component and in the class body, we'll have the render method where we
Bunu basite yapalm veya bileenden ithal ediyorsunuz ve Turdus'tan Paris'teki bir snf snfna,
in the end return some jsx and that is the jsx we used before.
sermaye karakteri geniletme stee bileeniyle ve
So I'll paste it in there,
O halde oraya yaptraym.
get rid of the part down there
u taraftan kurtulun.
and we're almost good to go, props now becomes this.props though because we're inside a class.
Ve neredeyse bir sahne ierisine girdiimiz iin sahne almaya neredeyse iyiyiz, ancak u anda bu sahne haline geliyor.
So thus far, this should work as before,
Bylece imdiye kadar bu daha nce olduu gibi almaldr.
well we also need to adjust the export here to capitalize the A,
De biz yararlanmak iin burada da ihracat ayarlamanz gerekir.
so this should work as before.
Yani bu daha nce olduu gibi almaldr.
Now I can use or set up the local UI state so the same state we used before in the entire course
imdi yerel gzleri devlete kullanabilir veya kurabilirim, bylece daha nce kullandmz durumu hep birlikte yaparm.
and there I'll have my name which is an empty string let's say initially and my age which could be null
Ve bo bir dize sahip ismimi alacam balangta yamda balangta bo
initially and then I'll add my method,
olabileceini syleyelim ve daha sonra yntemimi ekleyeceim.
the nameChangedHandler where I get my event object and where I then simply call this.setState to
Ad, olay nesnemi aldm yerde ileyiciyi deitirdi ve burada adn olay hedef deerine gncelletirmek iin
update the name to event.target.value
yalnzca bu ayar durumunu aryor.
and the goal is to execute the nameChangedHandler on every keystroke and I'll have my ageChangedHandler
Ve ama, her tu vuruunda isim deitirme iini yrtmek ve yam deiti.
where I get the event where the target is to call this.setState
Olay hedefin nereden alacan belirten ileyici, bu ayar durumunu armaktr.
and of course set the age to event.target.value on every keystroke.
Ve elbette her tu vuruunda iki olay hedef deeri yata.
And now we can bind our inputs at the onChange handler, bind it to this nameChangedHandler for the
Ve imdi girilerimizi onchange ileyicisine balayabiliriz, onu isim adna deitirilen bu isme deitiririz ve
name input, I'll simply distribute this over multiple lines to make it easier to read.
okumay kolaylatrmak iin basite distribtrlerin oklu satrlarna koyarz.
We now also need to bind the value to have two binding so that our type, our keystrokes are actually reflected
imdi, tm, iki basamaa sahip olmak iin bu deeri balamamz gerekir; bylece trn tu vurularmz girdi
in the input, so I'll
dosyasna yanstm oluruz.
bind this to this state name
Bu devlet adna balayn.
and now for a second input, also over multiple lines, I'll add onChange, bind this to this
Ve imdi, birden ok satrn zerine koyduumuz bir saniyeliine, change bind'in ekledii ey, buna balanyor.
ageChangedHandler and the value is equal to, whoops, this.state.age, just like that. So far that is all the stuff
Deitirilen tutucu ve deer, bu durumun WIP'lerine eittir H u an iin bu modlden nce
we learn before this module,
rendiimiz tm eylerdir.
it has nothing to do with redux,
Redux'la ilgisi yoktur.
we are managing the state of this component in itself,
Bu bileenin durumunu bizzat ynetiyoruz.
so inside the component. And that is what I meant on that slide where I talked about different types
Yani bileen iinde ve farkl Devlet trleri hakknda konutuum slaytta
of state, this is a typical use case of a local UI state you could say, whatever the user entered into the
anlattm ey, yerel bir Devletin tipik bir kullanm rneidir. Kullanc, muhtemelen alakal
inputs here probably isn't relevant to the entire application,
olmayan girdilere giren her eyi syleyebilir tm uygulama.
there is no need to store this in the global redux store.
Bunu global redox maazasnda saklamaya gerek yoktur.
You can absolutely store it in the state of that component because it only matters to that component,
Bu bileenin durumuna kesinlikle sokamazsnz, nk lm bileeniyle ilgilidir.
it does matter to the other components
Ortalama bileenler iin nemlidir.
as soon as this button is clicked, so here we'll pass an anonymous function so that we can pass some data
Bu kt durum burada toplanrsa, anonim bir ileve geeceiz, bylece baz eyleri pervane
along to the props here,
yanna gtreceiz.
so to person added, to whichever method we get here. I want to pass this.state.name and this.state.age
Bu yzden iki kii hangi yntemde olursa olsun, bu devlet adn ve bu devlet yan onunla
along with it
gemek isteyen ekledim.
so that in the container where we handle the person, add a prop where we connect a method to it, where
Dolaysyla, kiiyi, onu daha nce eklediimiz bir yntemi baladmz yere ynlendirdiimiz
we previously added on addPerson and executed this, that there, we now actually take advantage of
kapsaycda, bir kii eklemeyi veya gerekletirilen bir cmleyi uygulamaya cesaret edelim; aslnda, aldmz
the arguments we receive.
argmanlardan yararlanmaya cesaret ederiz.
So on addPerson of course refers to this method or this function we use to dispatch an action,
Bu nedenle reklamda bir kii tabii ki bu yntemi belirtiyor ya da bir eylemi gndermek iin disfonksiyonel olarak kullanyor.
well we now know that we get the name and age as arguments, so we should use that in the container, here
imdiyse, ad ve ya argman olarak aldmzn farkndayz, bu yzden burada onu konteynrda kullanmalyz.
we get name and age in the end.
Sonunda isim ve ya alyoruz.
So when we dispatch something, we can add name,set this is equal to name and age, set this is equal to age or
Bu yzden, bir eyi gnderirken, yaa eit ad ve yala eit kii ad ekleyebiliriz ya
one single property which we could name personData or payload or whatever you want which then hold name
da kii verileri veya yk belirtebileceimiz tek bir mlk ya da ismini ve yan
and age mapped to the respective argument.
ilgili argmana eletiren istediiniz her eyi istediiniz gibi ekleyebiliriz.
And now with that, we can go into our reducer and extract the value the user entered,
Ve imdi bununla reticimize gidebilir ve kullancnn girdii deeri karabiliriz.
so for the name, we would get action
Yani ad iin harekete geeceiz.
and then I used a key named personData
Sonra da kii bilgileri isimli bir anahtar kullandm.
and that would hold an object with name and age as keys,
Ve bu, Optik'i ad ve Alias tularyla birlikte tutar.
so I would access action.personData.name for the name and for the age, it would be action.person
Bu yzden, X-ists aksiyon adam veri adnn adn ve yan ise o yata eylemci kii
Data.age.
verisi olarak verecektim.
And now if we save all files and fix this error by going back to addPerson and setting age not to null but
imdi, tm dosyalar kaydedip, bu hatay, kiiyi eklemek ve u an iin ayar geri dndrmekle, ancak sitemde hata yazarak bo
to an empty string, typing mistake on my side,
bir dize koyarak dzeltiyoruz.
so to an empty string. If we do this,
Bo bir dize de bunu yaparz.
now we can enter Max 28 here, add person and we get Max 28 and if we change it, you'll see that's reflected
bunun bileenlerini hala burada silebileceini greceksiniz, fakat imdi her ikisini de bir araya getiriyoruz. daha
in our components which we still can delete here but now we're combining both, local UI state to
sonra uygulamanzn daha geni blmlerini etkileyen kiiyi yaratmak iin ii halledebiliriz.
handle the input and then still redux to handle the created person which affects broader parts of
imdi Max 28'i bizzat deneyebiliriz ve maksimum 28 oluruz ve
our application.
bunu deitirirsek
And I wanted to show you this, how to handle user input, how to handle that in a redux world and how to
Ve kullanc girdisini nasl ileyeceinizi redux dnyasnda nasl ele alacamz ve burada yalnzca
differentiate between local UI state as we use it here for information that really is only relevant
bu bileenle ve redoks iin ynetilen genel durumla ilgili bilgi iin kullandmz
to this component and to global state managed through redux for information which is important for our entire
gibi yerel UI durumu arasnda nasl ayrm yapacamz gstermek istedim tm bavurumuz iin nemli olan
application.
bilgi iin.